Guide to the Samuel Gruenberg Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Samuel Gruenberg papers
1880-1964
1939-1959
MS 1804
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The collection consists of correspondence, organizational records, personal papers, daily calendars, photographs, sermons, poetry, research materials, and other writings that document the activities and research of Samuel Gruenberg.
Gruenberg, Samuel
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Judaica Collection Curator, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Born in Romania, Samuel Gruenberg (1879-1959) was a rabbi, biblical scholar, and religious Zionist activist in Berlin, where he lived until 1939, when he emigrated to Palestine. He was active in the Mizrachi (religious Zionist) movement and after his arrival in Palestine, he served as the chairman of the Religious Council (Mo'atsah Datit) of Tel Aviv.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, organizational records, personal papers, daily calendars, photographs, sermons, poetry, research materials, and other writings that document the activities and research of Samuel Gruenberg.
Gruenberg, Samuel; Mizrachi
- Inventory
  - Collected materials, 1926-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
  - Organizations
    - Council for the Relief of Refugee Rabbis, 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Mizrachi organization, 1932-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5 - 6)
    - Sabbath observers, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Institution for Hebrew Language and Culture, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - The Religious Council of Tel Aviv
      - General, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1939-1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Financial reports, 1943-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Plans for establishment of the local religious councils, n. d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personal papers
    - Daily calendar, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Personal documents, 1880, 1939-1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Photographs, n. d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Writings
    - Biblical literature, 1935-1947 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Eulogies, speeches, sermons, 1925, 1939-1960 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - General, 1935-1946 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Notes and notebooks, 1938-1953 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Personal journal, 1898-1902 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Poetry, 1899-1951 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Rabbinic literature, 1915-1961 (Box 3, Folder 22 - 23)